<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the General Council of the Officers of the Army: agreed upon at Wallingford-house, 27th Octob. 1659. Thursday, 27th Octob. 1659. Ordered by the General Council of the Officers of the Army, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. Tho: Sandford Secret.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82153</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866874</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119162</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942623</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1001_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207847</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866874</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866874e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E1001[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the General Council of the Officers of the Army: agreed upon at Wallingford-house, 27th Octob. 1659. Thursday, 27th Octob. 1659. Ordered by the General Council of the Officers of the Army, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. Tho: Sandford Secret.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, printer to the Army, dwelling in Aldersgate Street next door to the Peacock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct: 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Republics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119162:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE GENERAL COUNCIL OF THE OFFICERS of the ARMY: Agreed upon at <hi>Wallingford</hi>-house, 27<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Octob.</hi> 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thursday,</hi> 27<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Octob. 1659.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>ORdered by the General Council of the Officers of the Army, That this Declaration be forthwith Printed and Published.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Tho: Sandford</hi> Secret.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the ARMY, dwelling in <hi>Aldersgate</hi> Street next door to the <hi>Peacock.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:119162:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119162:2"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF THE General Council OF THE Officers of the ARMY, Agreed upon at <hi>Wallingford</hi>-House the 27th. of <hi>October,</hi> 1659.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough all occasions are very unpleasing unto us, whereby we are necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Declaration,</hi> or <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal</hi> to justifie our selves, or our Actings to these <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and especially when (to do our selves right) we must necessarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist upon the <hi>failings</hi> and <hi>miscarriages</hi> of others:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119162:3"/>Yet seeing it hath pleased God by the hand of his wise and all-disposing Providence, to bring the Affairs of this <hi>Commonwealth</hi> into the State and Condition wherein now they are, We hold our selves obliged to give an <hi>accompt</hi> to the <hi>People</hi> thereof, and of our <hi>Proceedings</hi> therein: And conceiving it unnecessary to look back, or reflect upon the <hi>secret Designs</hi> which were <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived</hi> in that <hi>Parliament</hi> that ended the 12th. of <hi>April</hi> last, and broke forth in the late <hi>Insurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> and other parts of this Nation, to the extreme <hi>hazard</hi> of the <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Estates</hi> of all the <hi>well-affected</hi> people of this <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> and of whatsoever is <hi>valuable</hi> and <hi>dear</hi> unto them, We hope it will be sufficient at this time to declare as followeth.</p>
            <p>That before the <hi>re-calling</hi> of the late <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> we had divers consultations, and thoughts of heart, in what way and manner we might most effectually provide for the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>good Government</hi> of this <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> and at length, calling to mind those many great things which had been effected for the good of these Nations, during the Sitting of the said <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament;</hi> And being likewise fully <hi>perswaded,</hi> that the <hi>Government</hi> of these Nations might be most happily placed upon the <hi>Foundation of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> and that upon such <hi>Principles,</hi> as was then agreed upon by us, and hoping that through their <hi>experience</hi> in Affairs of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119162:3"/>we might most <hi>safely</hi> deliver the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Trust</hi> of these Nations into their <hi>hands,</hi> having likewise those further <hi>encouragements,</hi> That they, having lain for some years under that <hi>Rebuke,</hi> which God had given them for their <hi>former mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages,</hi> would thereby have been instructed to follow him more close, in the <hi>paths</hi> leading to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Righteousness:</hi> And also from some <hi>previous Meetings,</hi> with some worthy and leading <hi>Members</hi> of that <hi>House,</hi> who, upon debate with us, <hi>approved</hi> of the <hi>Principles</hi> aforesaid, and communicated them to divers of their fellow <hi>Members,</hi> That not onely old <hi>displeasures</hi> would have been <hi>forgotten,</hi> but that the single <hi>welfare</hi> and setled <hi>Government</hi> of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> would have been <hi>onely aimed at:</hi> and (as by one of the chief amongst themselves was exprest) having in <hi>Two moneths,</hi> or thereabouts, setled the <hi>Government</hi> of these Nations) go up with <hi>Moses</hi> to mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and <hi>die.</hi> And although we were not <hi>ignorant,</hi> that by their <hi>former inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> it was the opinion of many learned and able persons, who well understood Affairs of that kind, that the late <hi>Parliament</hi> was <hi>wholly Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved;</hi> and especially by the <hi>peoples succeeding Elections,</hi> who, upon Writs issued out to them for that purpose, <hi>reseized</hi> that <hi>Trust</hi> which they had <hi>formerly</hi> given them. And to this purpose let us repeat an <hi>expression</hi> of an eminent person; who sate as a <hi>Member</hi> in both the late <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119162:4"/>(and was deeply concerned in these late Actings) used upon another occasion in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the people by their Electing Members, to represent them in Parliament, had cut that knot with their own Sword, which by no other ways was capable to be dissolved or broken;</hi> Yet being <hi>desirous,</hi> like <hi>drowning</hi> men, (who are ready to sieze upon every Twig) to <hi>lay hold</hi> of any thing that had the least <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>Civil Authority,</hi> thereby hoping, not onely to keep these Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from <hi>sinking</hi> into <hi>Confusion,</hi> but to see it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily <hi>established</hi> upon the <hi>Basis</hi> aforementioned: We did think fit by our <hi>Declaration</hi> of the 6th. of <hi>May</hi> last, to <hi>invite</hi> the <hi>Members</hi> of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to return to the Exercise and Discharge of the <hi>Trust</hi> formerly reposed in them; which being by them accordingly accepted, soon after their Sitting, we did, in a most <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>solemn</hi> manner, present our <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Address</hi> unto them, wherein was contained the sum of our desires and principles aforesaid: To which we had, to our <hi>great content,</hi> ample assurance of the Parliaments good <hi>acceptance</hi> exprest not only by their <hi>hearty thanks</hi> at that time, but after by their <hi>Votes, approving</hi> divers of the same, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to provide for others, referred the same to several <hi>Committees</hi> of their own Members, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpose.</p>
            <p>Things being brought (as we then hoped) to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119162:4"/>a good posture, tending towards <hi>Settlement</hi> &amp; <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> we did expect the speedy <hi>fruits</hi> thereof, when contrary to our expectations, instead of an effectual and full Act of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> (desired in our third <hi>Proposal,</hi> as the <hi>medium</hi> of <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to our selves, and other the well-affected peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> who had served under the former <hi>Governments,</hi> and of <hi>encouragement</hi> to us, and them again with <hi>chearfulness</hi> under them, to <hi>discharge</hi> our <hi>duties</hi> in our and their respective places and stations) we found it <hi>a long time</hi> to hang in suspence, and at last (after divers and earnest <hi>importunities</hi> to many Members of Parliament) and Act of <hi>Indempnity</hi> came forth so <hi>imperfect</hi> and <hi>ineffectual</hi> for the ends expected, as that not onely our <hi>selves,</hi> but divers <hi>others</hi> were left liable to <hi>ruine</hi> at their <hi>pleasures,</hi> and subject to <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>molestation</hi> at Law, for <hi>Acts</hi> done for the publick Service; as well during the time of their <hi>former</hi> Sitting, as under other suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>Governments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for what concerned our desires in our 12th. proposal, (for the <hi>union</hi> of the <hi>Forces</hi> of this Commonwealth) wherein we did <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously</hi> own the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> to be <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chief of the land Forces of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> and concerning which, we had <hi>assurance given,</hi> that the same should be granted in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: we were not less <hi>deceived</hi> in our <hi>expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> his <hi>Commission</hi> being restrained to the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119162:5"/>of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and limited to the fixth of <hi>May</hi> next ensuing; or to be <hi>revoked</hi> at <hi>pleasure:</hi> and the further to <hi>abridge</hi> him of the <hi>Authority</hi> necessarily belonging to the <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chief</hi> of an Army, for the good <hi>Government</hi> thereof: And to render the Army wholly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servient to their will, they Resolved, <hi>That all Commissions should be given out by the Speaker,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening a way to decline or cast out whom they pleased, without so much as hearing: which nevertheless, for <hi>peace</hi> sake, was <hi>submitted</hi> unto by the Army; it being then affirmed, that no such thing had been, or ever would be done in Parliament, which proved otherwise in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel, as will be hereafter more particularly <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>factions</hi> hereupon grew up in the <hi>Army,</hi> what new moulding, changing and transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof (to the discomposure of the whole) how prodio were made, headed, and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by divers <hi>Members</hi> sitting in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>strengthened;</hi> not onely by <hi>bringing</hi> divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons into <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>prejudiced</hi> mindes, but by <hi>removing</hi> faithful <hi>Officers</hi> into <hi>remote</hi> parts of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> without any <hi>cause</hi> shewen, or consultations had with the <hi>Commander in Chief</hi> thereupon, was not onely <hi>notoriously</hi> known by those, who are concerned in Military Affairs, but <hi>obvious</hi> to common observations. By which means the aforementioned <hi>Design</hi> of a <hi>general
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119162:5"/>Insurrection</hi> took further <hi>encouragement,</hi> spread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it self into every part of this Nation: and being now grown ripe (though by the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full goodness of God prevented in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) broke forth in <hi>Cheshire</hi> the first of <hi>August</hi> last, where a considerable Number of <hi>Horse</hi> and <hi>Foot</hi> were speedily drawn together, and <hi>formed</hi> into an <hi>Army,</hi> under the Command of Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> and others; For the suppression of which, a convenient Number of the Army were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to march under the Command of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor General <hi>Lambert,</hi> and (through the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God upon their faithful and chearful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours) that <hi>Enemy</hi> was <hi>suddenly</hi> routed and <hi>subdued,</hi> and the whole Nation reduced again to <hi>quietness,</hi> with little loss of <hi>bloud,</hi> and less of other the sad <hi>marks</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> which usually attend a <hi>Civil war.</hi> The full sence of which <hi>Mercy</hi> put it into the hearts and mindes of some <hi>Officers</hi> of that part of the <hi>Army,</hi> to <hi>meet</hi> and consider how the same might be <hi>improved</hi> to the glory of God, and <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> And thereupon resolved upon a <hi>Paper,</hi> which, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a <hi>Letter,</hi> they sent to the Lord <hi>Fleet-wood,</hi> desiring if he saw it fit, to <hi>communicate</hi> it to a General Council of Officers for their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation: His Excellency (desiring to put the same into such a way as might not savour of <hi>offence</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or any member thereof) consulted with Sir <hi>Arthur Hesilrig</hi> thereupon,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119162:6"/>and in order to the taking further <hi>counsel</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>desired</hi> that he, Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> and Major <hi>Salwey,</hi> would meet with himself to consider of such course to be taken in this matter, as might best sute with the present occasion and posture of affairs: But <hi>contrary</hi> to expectation and all <hi>ingenuity</hi> (although a meeting was agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) the next day Sir <hi>Arthur Hesilrig informed</hi> the <hi>House</hi> of the said <hi>Paper,</hi> representing that some dangerous <hi>design</hi> against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> was on foot in the <hi>Army,</hi> and intentions to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce a new <hi>Government,</hi> by setting up a <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle person,</hi> though that Paper was manifestly contrary to any such end or purpose, as by its being exposed to publique view, will more fully appear. Whereupon, the House possest with <hi>prejudice</hi> upon this <hi>misinformation,</hi> fell into high debates, expressing great heat and anger against the Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> and several other <hi>faithful</hi> Officers of the <hi>Brigade,</hi> from whence the <hi>Paper</hi> came, although they were truly informed by the Lord <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> and others, that the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> gave no <hi>consent,</hi> nor had any hand in the same, but endeavoured the <hi>suppression</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of both before and after his coming to Town; And also although neither the Paper it self, nor the matter of fact was before them, nor the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons admitted to <hi>speak</hi> for themselves, so that now it was apparent, that those <hi>factions</hi> already laid, began again to <hi>pursue,</hi> what they had in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119162:6"/>
               <hi>prospect</hi> and <hi>design</hi> more <hi>openly</hi> and vigorously then before. Hereupon the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> thought it their duty to represent to the <hi>Parliament</hi> their <hi>innocency,</hi> and to <hi>vindicate</hi> themselves from those <hi>aspersions</hi> which were <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily</hi> and <hi>falsly</hi> charged upon them, and withall (to <hi>obviate</hi> the afore-mentioned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs) to desire that the Army might receive their <hi>Commissions,</hi> with the advice of such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, who by experience had the knowledge of their <hi>abilities</hi> and <hi>fitness</hi> for <hi>service,</hi> and that they might not be turned out <hi>arbitrarily,</hi> but by the usual and known way of a <hi>Court Martial,</hi> and being willing to <hi>bury</hi> all <hi>prejudices</hi> by-past, they desired only that some <hi>Checque</hi> and <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement</hi> might be put upon such, who (for the future) should endeavour to beget <hi>mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>understandings</hi> between the Parliament and them.</p>
            <p>And lastly, asserting the <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Rights</hi> belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to all the People of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> as also to themselves, of <hi>presenting</hi> in a peaceable and <hi>submissive</hi> way their desires to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which being expressed in our <hi>Representation and Petition,</hi> was humbly presented to them on the 5th. of this instant <hi>October.</hi> The <hi>reception</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being accompanied with the <hi>Thanks</hi> of the <hi>House,</hi> gave again renewed hopes of a right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding between the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Army.</hi> Both which <hi>Representation</hi> and <hi>Petition,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119162:7"/>together with the <hi>Answer</hi> of the <hi>House</hi> thereunto, have been already exposed to publick view.</p>
            <p>The general Council of Officers, when they agreed the aforesaid <hi>Representation</hi> and <hi>Petition,</hi> resolved then, (to the end the true state of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs might be <hi>commanicated</hi> unto those of the <hi>Army,</hi> who were equally concerned with them) <hi>That Copies thereof should be sent to the Officers of the several Regiments, Troops, Companies, and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons, in</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them (in case they were free thereunto) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with them in their just desires:</hi> And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise appointing the said <hi>Letter</hi> to be <hi>Signed</hi> by a <hi>Committee</hi> of Officers which they had appointed for that purpose.</p>
            <p>The Parliament upon the 10th. of <hi>October,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into debate the said humble <hi>Representation</hi> and <hi>Petition,</hi> Resolved in answer to the first Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal, <hi>That the Officers of the Army had received, and should from time to time receive marks of the favour of the Parliament, and countenance answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their faithfulness and merit.</hi> Which, how far it did answer the reasonable part of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, we leave to all indifferent persons to judge, when they shall duely weigh the following pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>In the afternoon of the same day they did resolve, that this be the answer to the second Proposal, <hi>That it is the duty of all Persons, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Members of Parliament, to informe the House
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119162:7"/>of any thing which in their apprehension may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the publick safety. And, that it is the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed right of the Parliament, to receive and debate those Informations, and resolve what they think fit thereupon.</hi> Where we cannot choose but take notice, that this being applied to the said second <hi>Proposal,</hi> it asserts it to be the <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>all</hi> persons to <hi>informe</hi> the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>any</hi> thing, be it never so <hi>frivolous</hi> and <hi>false,</hi> which in their apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>concern</hi> the <hi>publick safety.</hi> And that it is the <hi>undoubted</hi> right of the Parliament to <hi>receive</hi> and <hi>debate</hi> those <hi>informations,</hi> and to <hi>resolve</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon if they think sit, the <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>destruction</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> and their <hi>Families,</hi> who are <hi>informed</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, before the said persons be <hi>heard,</hi> or their Case truly <hi>stated</hi> before them.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Tuesday</hi> the next day after, a <hi>Bill</hi> was brought into the <hi>House,</hi> and, contrary to the <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual</hi> Orders of <hi>Parliament,</hi> thrice read in one and the same day, and passed into an Act, thereby enacting, <hi>That all Orders, Ordinances, and Acts made by any single Person and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or by both or either of them, or otherwise, or by any Assembly, or Convention pretending to have Authority of Parliament, from and after the</hi> 19. <hi>day of</hi> April 1653. <hi>and before the</hi> 7. <hi>of</hi> May 1659. <hi>and which have not been, or shall not be enacted, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or confirmed by this present Parliament, be,</hi> should be, <hi>and were thereby declared, deemed, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and adjudged to be of no force or effect, from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119162:8"/>and after the said</hi> 7. <hi>of</hi> May, 1659. which was altogether contrary to what was humbly desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the third <hi>Preposal</hi> of the <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress</hi> of the 12. of <hi>May,</hi> 1659. and to what they gave us just grounds to expect, having commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Proposal to a Committee of their own, to bring in such <hi>Bill</hi> or <hi>Bils</hi> for that purpose, as they thought necessary.</p>
            <p>And in the same <hi>Bill</hi> it was likewise contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That no Person or Persons should after the</hi> 11. of October (being the very day that the said Act was hastily passed) <hi>raise Moneys without consent of the people in Parliament,</hi> thereby in an instant putting a <hi>doubt</hi> and <hi>discomposure</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all mens mindes that are concerned in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that nature, so that if any thing should cross such their <hi>strange</hi> proceedings, the Army might be necessitated to that odious <hi>Refuge</hi> of <hi>Free Quarter,</hi> or else be <hi>exposed</hi> to such <hi>provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> through the want of a fit <hi>provision</hi> for their subsistence, as might alienate their <hi>mindes</hi> from that <hi>care</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> that is incumbent on them, for the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>security</hi> of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>And not only so, but the other <hi>mischiefs</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rising from this <hi>precipitate Act</hi> will prove <hi>many</hi> and <hi>great.</hi> For then the most <hi>choice</hi> and <hi>godly</hi> Ministers of the Nation, will be found to be <hi>comprised</hi> herein, and <hi>themselves</hi> and their <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances</hi> altogether avoided, and great numbers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119162:8"/>of <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>scandalous</hi> Ministers, which have been <hi>ejected</hi> for near the space of <hi>six years</hi> past, will then be re-estated; the <hi>Adventurers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> left at a loss and in confusion; the <hi>Rebels</hi> that were <hi>transplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> there, be at their <hi>liberty</hi> to <hi>return;</hi> the <hi>union</hi> made between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> rendred <hi>invalid;</hi> All the <hi>Compositions</hi> and <hi>Assurances</hi> thereupon given and made to the <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to the <hi>excepted</hi> persons and <hi>Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> made <hi>insignificant;</hi> divers <hi>Souldiers,</hi> who have for a long time in our former times of <hi>Difficulty,</hi> and have since either <hi>voluntarily</hi> upon <hi>reducements,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise left the Army, and betaken themselves to several <hi>Occupations</hi> and <hi>Callings</hi> within several Towns, and <hi>Occupations</hi> for <hi>a Livelihood</hi> to them and their Families, are not only for the future <hi>disinabled</hi> to <hi>profess</hi> and <hi>use</hi> the same, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise left liable to the <hi>severity</hi> of the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Customes,</hi> for all things done <hi>contrary</hi> thereunto since the 7. of <hi>May</hi> 1659; All <hi>Estates</hi> conferred on any <hi>person</hi> or <hi>persons</hi> by former <hi>Governments,</hi> though upon never so <hi>valuable</hi> and <hi>publick</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations, left in a <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>uncertain</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to the <hi>unravelling</hi> and <hi>unknown</hi> discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posure of several mens <hi>estates</hi> and <hi>interests,</hi> the <hi>consequences</hi> whereof will in short time <hi>appear</hi> by the <hi>sad</hi> effects of multiplying <hi>suits</hi> and vexation of <hi>innocent</hi> persons, if the said <hi>Act</hi> could be deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119162:9"/>as <hi>valid.</hi> Concerning which we shall <hi>adde</hi> no more but, that had not <hi>strange</hi> precipitancy and <hi>design</hi> driven it on, it could hardly be believed, that any <hi>Supreme Authority</hi> would ever have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed a people to such <hi>inconveniences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Things being thus prepared in order to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ends, the next day (being <hi>Wednesday</hi>) the Parliament hoping they had a <hi>great</hi> influence upon part of the <hi>Army,</hi> and conceiving they had by their late <hi>Acts</hi> sufficiently <hi>perplexed</hi> those whom they doubted might oppose them, and that the <hi>Government</hi> of these Nations was so sure in their own hands, as in all probability things might come to <hi>confusion,</hi> except mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>themselves,</hi> proceed <hi>vigorously</hi> to put their designs in practice. In the morning the <hi>Doors</hi> of the <hi>Lobby,</hi> by their <hi>appointment</hi> being fast <hi>shut</hi> and <hi>guarded,</hi> that none might by any means come near to the <hi>House,</hi> or understand their <hi>proceedings: Occasion</hi> is administred from one of the <hi>Letters</hi> which was <hi>signed</hi> by several <hi>Officers,</hi> according to appointment of the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council,</hi> and sent to a <hi>Regiment</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> and produced by a Member of the House (it being of no other purport then the <hi>sending</hi> the said <hi>Representation and Petition</hi> to one of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of the <hi>Army</hi> as is before-mentioned) Yet nevertheless they <hi>fell foul</hi> upon the several <hi>Officers</hi> who had <hi>subscribed</hi> it, and took <hi>this rise</hi> in pursuance of their <hi>former intent</hi> to make a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119162:9"/>plain <hi>breach</hi> upon the <hi>Army;</hi> and thereupon <hi>vote</hi> out of their Commands (without hearing any one person speak for himself, or examine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the persons whose names were subscribed, were their hand-writing or not) the Lord <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> General <hi>Disborow,</hi> and <hi>seven</hi> other <hi>Colonels</hi> and <hi>Field Officers,</hi> disposing <hi>divers</hi> of their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> to the <hi>Officers</hi> next under them: And as they did the <hi>day before,</hi> so now, they hastily pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it into an <hi>Act</hi> before they rose, for the <hi>making void</hi> the Lord <hi>Fleetwoods</hi> Commission, and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesting</hi> the <hi>Command</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> in <hi>seven</hi> persons, whereof himself was one, some of whom were the <hi>principal</hi> in carrying on this whole <hi>design.</hi> Whereupon the House <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed,</hi> and <hi>three</hi> of the said <hi>number</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately <hi>repaired</hi> to the <hi>Speakers chamber:</hi> And having <hi>provided</hi> themselves of <hi>six</hi> barrels of <hi>Powder,</hi> and a <hi>quantity</hi> of <hi>Provision,</hi> forthwith gave out <hi>orders</hi> for Colonel <hi>Morley's</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>draw</hi> thither; as also to divers other <hi>Regiments, Troops</hi> and <hi>Companies,</hi> which they thought would be most <hi>sure</hi> to them; And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise gave order to Colonel <hi>Okey</hi> to draw his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment</hi> to the <hi>Palace-yard,</hi> upon which he <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi> to <hi>Tuttle fields</hi> with four of his <hi>troops;</hi> and from thence (having sent one into the <hi>Palace yard</hi> he <hi>marched</hi> with the other three into <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> for <hi>countenancing</hi> the drawing together the <hi>Militia forces,</hi> in order to a <hi>conjunction</hi> with them,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119162:10"/>which proved there <hi>ineffectuall,</hi> but had other <hi>suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> where by like <hi>directions,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Thomsons</hi> Regiment <hi>drew together</hi> under the command of their <hi>Lieutenant Colonel;</hi> and that no endeavors might be wanting, Orders were sent to Colonel <hi>Hackers</hi> Regiment, <hi>quartering</hi> in and about <hi>Leicestershire,</hi> and other <hi>Troops</hi> in other remote places in the Country, to <hi>march</hi> to <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi> with all speed; the <hi>tendency</hi> whereof must naturally lead to the <hi>engaging</hi> the <hi>City; Country,</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> in <hi>blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Officers of the Army having received <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice</hi> of these <hi>things,</hi> and being greatly <hi>amused</hi> at so <hi>strange</hi> and <hi>sudden</hi> a mutation, and that the <hi>office</hi> of <hi>Commander in chief,</hi> should be <hi>this minute</hi> executed by the hand of my Lord <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> and the <hi>next</hi> by the hands of Sr <hi>Arthur Hesilrig,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Morley,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Walton;</hi> and that <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> were so <hi>speedily</hi> hastned out for the <hi>drawing</hi> of <hi>force</hi> together, were in great doubt that such <hi>strange</hi> and <hi>violent courses</hi> did portend some <hi>sad</hi> and <hi>fatal</hi> event: And thereupon they judged it their <hi>duty,</hi> for <hi>preservation</hi> of <hi>themselves,</hi> their <hi>friends,</hi> and honest <hi>interest</hi> in the <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> to draw together in <hi>Arms,</hi> and march to the <hi>Palace yard</hi> at <hi>Westminster</hi> (the place they had appointed for their <hi>rendezvous</hi>) to understand the <hi>reasons</hi> and <hi>grounds</hi> of their so assembling themselves together: And being <hi>arrived</hi> there, and perceiving that several <hi>Companies</hi> of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119162:10"/>
               <hi>Morley</hi>'s Regiment were placed in the <hi>Hall, Gatehouse, Clockhouse,</hi> and <hi>Exchequer Chamber,</hi> and thereabouts, in <hi>hostile manner,</hi> all <hi>endeavours</hi> were used to <hi>inform</hi> them of the true <hi>state</hi> of <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,</hi> and to <hi>draw</hi> them to such a <hi>compliance</hi> with the rest of their <hi>brethren</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> as might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the <hi>effusion</hi> of <hi>blood;</hi> but finding them, by the <hi>perswasion</hi> of their <hi>leaders, obstinately</hi> bent to <hi>oppose,</hi> We found our selves <hi>necessitated</hi> to put the <hi>Forces</hi> into a posture of <hi>defence;</hi> and for the <hi>grounds</hi> and <hi>reasons</hi> aforementioned, (as also, that they might not be futher <hi>encouraged</hi> and <hi>counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced</hi> in such a <hi>dangerous</hi> opposition, to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent <hi>hazard</hi> of the publick <hi>peace</hi>) to put a <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod</hi> and <hi>determination</hi> to the Parliaments <hi>meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> together; and think our selves yet further <hi>obliged,</hi> for <hi>preventing</hi> of the manifold <hi>evils</hi> and <hi>inconveniences,</hi> which must necessarily fall upon the other <hi>good people</hi> of the Nation, as well as our <hi>selves,</hi> by reason of the severall <hi>Orders, Acts, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> Acts or other <hi>Declaration,</hi> or any of them, <hi>enacted, made,</hi> or <hi>past</hi> on <hi>Munday</hi> the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of this instant <hi>October,</hi> and on <hi>Tuesday</hi> and <hi>Wednesday</hi> then next following, to declare them and every of <hi>them, null</hi> and <hi>void</hi> to all intents and purposes; And do hereby declare <hi>them,</hi> and every of <hi>them,</hi> and every <hi>clause</hi> and <hi>sentence</hi> therein, <hi>invalid, null</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> to all intents and purposes: And likewise all <hi>Acts, Orders,</hi> and <hi>proceedings</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>had</hi> or <hi>done,</hi> in as <hi>full,</hi> and <hi>ample manner,</hi> as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119162:11"/>if the said <hi>Orders, Acts,</hi> pretended <hi>Acts</hi> or <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> and every of <hi>them,</hi> had never been. All which we thought fit to <hi>publish</hi> and <hi>declare,</hi> to the end all persons concerned may take notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and no <hi>person</hi> whatsoever <hi>suffer</hi> any further <hi>prejudice</hi> thereby, hoping that all <hi>peaceable,</hi> well minded, and <hi>unprejudiced</hi> persons will <hi>acquiesce</hi> in the <hi>necessity</hi> and justice thereof.</p>
            <p>And now we shall conclude, in declaring to the <hi>World,</hi> that it is upon our hearts, and we ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desire, and shall <hi>endeavour,</hi> that a due <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> may be assured to all the <hi>free born people</hi> of these <hi>Nations,</hi> both as <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Christians:</hi> that a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>through Reformation of the Law</hi> may be effected, as also that a <hi>Faithful, godly,</hi> and <hi>pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful gospel-preaching Ministery</hi> may be <hi>encouraged</hi> and <hi>provided</hi> for, by some certain way that may be <hi>less troublesome</hi> to them, and <hi>less vexatious</hi> to the people, then that of <hi>Tithes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we do further Declare, That we have no <hi>aim</hi> or <hi>ends</hi> to set up a <hi>Military</hi> or <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government over this <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> but have already <hi>provided</hi> that the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Executive</hi> part of Government may be be lodged in a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of safety,</hi> and they obliged in a <hi>short</hi> time, to prepare such a <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> as may best suit and comport with a <hi>free State</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> without a <hi>Single Person, King-ship</hi> or <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Pears:</hi> And that we shall to the <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most</hi> of our <hi>endeavours,</hi> labor to obtain those
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119162:11"/>desirable things so <hi>often</hi> declared for; and to maintain and preserve the <hi>Peace</hi> of these Nations in our several Stations and Places, and shall hope that God for his own <hi>Glory,</hi> and the <hi>good</hi> of his own <hi>People,</hi> will give a blessed end of these <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> by a happy <hi>Settlement</hi> upon the principles formerly declared for; and which have been, and still are so earnestly breathed after, by all those who truly fear his Name,</p>
            <p>Who, we doubt not, being truly <hi>sensible</hi> of the many <hi>temptations</hi> besetting us on every hand, the great difficulties we labor under, (and know not what farther <hi>straits</hi> a day may bring forth) will say on our behalfs, <hi>who are sufficient for these things?</hi> And out of former <hi>experiences,</hi> being <hi>taught,</hi> that the Lord <hi>is a present help in time of trouble,</hi> will <hi>cry aloud</hi> for us before the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> That the Lord himself may <hi>appear,</hi> and carry on his own work in our hands. And if it shall <hi>please</hi> him by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> to stir up <hi>those</hi> that <hi>fear</hi> his <hi>Name</hi> to be <hi>instant</hi> on our <hi>behalfs,</hi> We shall not fear what <hi>evil</hi> men can do unto us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>